A Guide to the Helene and Estelle Philibert Papers, 1947-1964
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Helene and Estelle Philibert Papers, 1947-1964.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 90.3
1 linear ft.
Helene Philibert.; Estelle Philibert.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1990.
Biographical/Historical Information
Helene and Estelle Philibert, researchers of Alexandria, Virginia, were employed by the Department of the Navy in a confidential capacity for many years and later assisted with naval history projects.
Scope and Content Information
Papers include notes, printed pamphlets, brochures, catalogues and newspaper clippings, as well as typescripts and copies of documents. They pertain to the Philiberts' research on different topics and individuals. The bulk of the collection pertains to Helene Philibert's research on John Paul Jones (1747-1792) for Samuel Eliot Morisons's (1887-1976) work on Jones entitled John Paul Jones: a Sailor's Biography, c.1959. The Jones research contains copies of documents pertaining to or written by Jones. These papers concern primarily his arrival in America and his service in the United States Navy during the Revolution (1776-1781.)
Also includes correspondence between Samuel Eliot Morison and Helene Philibert documenting the research process, and clippings and photos pertaining to Jones and to Morison's career. Other topics and individuals include the Montague, Minor and Weeks families; the Ball family, especially Mary Washington Ball (1708-1789); the Marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834), especially his 1824-25 visit to the United States, and the Society of the American Friends of Lafayette; and the Mason family, especially John Mason, the growth of Washington, D.C., and Gunston Hall.
Organization
This collection has been organized into 7 series:
Series 1. John Paul Jones Research
Series 2. Samuel Eliot Morison Publications
Series 3. Ball Family Research
Series 4. Lafayette Research
Series 5. Mason Family Research
Series 6. Montague/Minor/Weeks Research
Series 7. Miscellaneous Materials
Series 8. Oversize Materials
Index Terms
Persons:
Philibert, Helene.; Forrestal, James, 1892- 1949.; Jones, John Paul, 1747-1792.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834.; Morison, Samuel Eliot, 1887-1976.; Washington, Mary Ball, 1708- 1789.
Family Names:
Ball family.; Mason family.; Minor family.; Montague family.; Weeks family.
Corporate Names:
United States--Navy--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.
Geographical Names:
United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Naval operations.; Virginia-- Genealogy.
Contents List
- John Paul Jones Research, ca. 1760-1964., 31 folders. (Box-folder 1:1-2:31)
  - Photostats and transcripts. ca. 1760-1947., 26 folders. (Box-folder 1:1-1:26.)
    Photostats and transcripts of original documents used by the Philiberts and Samuel Morison in their research on John Paul Jones. Also includes one microfilm reel of photostats from Harvard University Library relating to Jones's niece, Janette Taylor, and used by the Philiberts while doing research for Samuel Eliot Morison.
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1760-1769. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1770-1772. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1773-1775. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jan.-June 1776. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jul.-Dec. 1776. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jan.-Mar. 1777. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Apr.-Sept. 1777. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Oct.-Dec. 1777. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jan.-Mar. 1778. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Apr.-Jun. 1778. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jul.-Aug. 1778 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Sept.-Oct. 1778. (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Nov.-Dec. 1778. (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jan.-June 1779. (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jul.-Dec. 1779. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jan.-Jun 1780. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jul.-Dec. 1780. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jan.-Mar. 1781. (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Mar.-Dec. 1781. (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1782-1785. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Jan. 1786. (Box-folder 1:21)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Feb. 1786-1789. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1790-1799. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1800-1839. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Photostats and transcripts, Aug. 1846-1852; 1947. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Photostats and transcripts, n.d. (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1964., 3 folders. (Box-folder 2:27-2:29)
    Correspondence between Helene Philibert and Samuel Eliot Morison, as well as others, regarding the research on John Paul Jones; also includes some personal correspondence between the Philiberts and Samuel Eliot Morison.
    - Correspondence, 1947-1957. (Box-folder 2:27)
    - Correspondence, Mar.-Oct. 1958. (Box-folder 2:28)
    - Correspondence, Nov. 1958-1964 and n.d. (Box-folder 2:29)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 2:30)
    Typed notes and excerpts from primary and secondary source material relating to John Paul Jones; concerns primarily his early life before and upon reaching the United States in 1773.
  - Photographs and pictures, n.d. (Box-folder 2:31)
    Photographs and pictures of John Paul Jones and his contemporaries, ships which they commanded, commemorative medals, and his birthplace. Most are official U.S. Navy photographs.
- Samuel Eliot Morison Publications., 2 folders. (Box-folder 2:32-2:33)
  - Miscellaneous articles. (Box-folder 2:32)
    Printed articles by Samuel Eliot Morison on various subjects.
  - John Paul Jones articles. (Box-folder 2:33)
    Printed articles by Samuel Eliot Morison on John Paul Jones including several manuscript copies of his article on the Willie Jones-John Paul Jones tradition.
- Ball Family Research (Box-folder 2:34-3:40)
  - Photostats and transcripts, 1601-1939. (Box-folder 2:34-2:37)
    Photostats and transcripts of original documents used by the Philiberts for their research on Mary Ball Washington and the Ball family.
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1601-1682. (Box-folder 2:34)
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1700-1739. (Folder 2:35)
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1741-1762. (Box-folder 2:36)
    - Photostats and transcripts, 1775-1939 and n.d. (Box-folder 2:37)
  - Correspondence, 1874-1976. (Box-folder 2:38)
    The Philiberts' correspondence relating to research on Mary Ball Washington.
  - Biography, n.d. (Box-folder 2:39)
    Incomplete manuscript of biography of Mary Ball Washington, probably by Helene or Estelle Philibert.
  - Printed material. (Box-folder 3:40)
    Printed material on the Ball family; includes genealogical charts, genealogies, and pictures.
- Lafayette Research. (Box-folder 3:41-3:44a)
  - Photostats and transcripts, 17??-19?? (Box-folder 3:41-3:42)
    Photostats and transcripts used by Helene Philibert; concerns the Marquis de Lafayette, especially his visit to the United States in 1824.
  - Photographs and pictures, ca. 1960-ca. 1979. (Box-folder 3:43)
    Photographs, negatives, and pictures of: Lafayette; Commodore Charles Morris, Commander of the ship that took Lafayette across the Atlantic for his 1824-25 tour of the United States; and memorials to Lafayette.
  - Newspaper clippings, ca. 1800-ca. 1979. (Box-folder 3:44)
    Newspaper clippings pertaining to the Marquis de Lafayette and the Society of the Friends of Lafayette.
  - Printed material, ca. 1930-1979. (Box-folder 3:44a)
    Miscellaneous printed material relating to the American Friends of Lafayette, commemorative ceremonies in honor of Lafayette, and manuscript collections containing Lafayette memorabilia and papers.
- Mason Family Research., 3:45-3:48
  - Photostats and transcripts, ca. 1800-ca. 1979. (Box-folder 3:45)
    Photostats and transcripts relating to the Mason family; including George Mason of Gunston Hall and his son, General John Mason.
  - Correspondence, ca. 1930-ca. 1979. (Box-folder 3:46)
    Correspondence of the Philiberts relating to their research on the Mason family.
  - Photographs and pictures. (Box-folder 3:47)
    Photographs of portraits of General and Mrs. John Mason and other pictures relating to the Mason family.
  - Printed material, ca. 1970-ca. 1979. (Box-folder 3:48)
    Genealogical charts of the Mason family.
- Montague/Minor/Weeks Research. (Box-folder 3:49-3:52)
  - Photostats and transcripts, ca. 1600-ca. 1899. (Box-folder 3:49-3:50)
    Photostats and transcripts relating to the Montague, Minor, and Weeks families.
  - Correspondence, ca. 1930-ca. 1979. (Box-folder 3:51)
    Correspondence relating to research on the Montague, Minor, and Weeks families.
  - Printed material, ca. 1960-1969. (Box-folder 3:52)
    Printed genealogical material relating to Peter Montague and his descendants.
- Miscellaneous Materials. (Box-folder 3:53-3:56)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, ca. 1930-ca. 1939. (Box-folder 3:53)
    Correspondence including several letters to Malcolm McConihe, Democratic National Committeeman, from James Roosevelt, Cordell Hull and others. Also includes a letter from Melvin Laird to Helene Philibert.
  - Miscellaneous documents, ca. 1800-ca. 1979. (Box-folder 3:54)
    Several nineteenth-century documents and letters relating to the Kearney family. Also includes Helene Philibert's Red Cross certificate and a few poems by unknown authors.
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 1947-1948. (Box-folder 3:55)
    Photographs of James Forrestal, Secretary of Defense, in the late 1940s. Helene Philibert was a member of Forrestal's immediate staff and he personally inscribed several of these photos.
  - Miscellaneous printed material, 1956-1970. (Box-folder 3:56)
    Catalogues of manuscript collections at the U.S. Naval Academy Museum and of United States Naval history sources.
- Oversize Materials., 12 items. (Oversize 1X Oversize)
  - Deed, between Chesapeake Corp. and Montague Memorial Association, 14 July 1948., Photostat.
  - Indenture, between William Montague and Cornelius Sullivan, 4 Oct. 1870., Photostat.
    Entered in Deed Book No. 26, Lancaster County.
  - Deed, Cornelius Sullivan to Armistead Palmer, Lancaster County, 19 Jan. 1818., Photostat.
  - Will of William Montague, 21 Oct. 1763.
    Entered Middlesex County Will Book E, 1760-1772.
  - Will of William Montague, 2 Dec 1753., Photostat.
    Entered in Middlesex County Will Book D, 1748-1760.
  - Inventory of Montague estate. n.d., Photostat.
    Entered in Lancaster County Inventories, 1650-1719.
  - Land grant, Francis Nicholson to Peter Montague, 24 Oct. 1702.
  - Agreement between Augustine Washington II and Principio Iron Works, 31 May 1726., Photostat.
  - James Forrestal portraits., 2 items. With personal inscriptions to Estelle Philibert.
  - James Forrestal photographs., 2 items with personal inscriptions to Helene Philibert.